hello welcome to
B&B uh episode number nine the B&B
connection got it's been a while Brad it
yes I've been trying to get uh Brad to
come on but he's too busy with his
traveling the world with his conferences
and this isn't true Brad's usually
bugging me but uh anyway today we have a
unique episode we're going to just
discuss some of uh uh the research that
we've been doing that my lab has been
doing um it's all the glute lab yeah you
see that you see glute lab on all the P
reviewed research now right no it's
actually it's all done in Brad's lab but
uh I'm always happy because Brad and I
you know he we talk about these studies
and then he does all the work and then I
I'll look over it give my two cents and
then I'm on the paper with him so um
but we actually have a long list of when
whenever you do one of these studies you
three more pop up that you want to do
it's like you know research is never
ending
so um hopefully when I finish my PhD
we'll just keep cranking because I'll
have a lot of good sport science uh
technology and he has his lab and I'm
actually amassing a decent little lab
myself I've got to make a couple more
big purchases but uh anyway um so there
we're today's episode we're going to
discuss five different papers if we have
time um that we haven't and some uh four
of them no three of them are published
one is has been accepted right Brad and
then one of them is in
review but
uh um so I'll be able to link three of
the five in the blog post but um in time
all five will hopefully be up um well I
know one one of them will for sure sure
the other one I can't the other one I
can't see not being published but uh you
never know with peer reviewers anyway
the first article looks at bodybuilding
versus powerlifting Brad what's the
title title is um effects of different
volume equated resistance training
loading strategies on muscular
adaptations in well-trained men that is
a mouth call okay accepted back in April
of 2014 of this year and how how many
subjects were there
Brad well we started with 20 we ended up
with 17 there was nine in one group and
eight in the other and how many uh years
of experience do they have around a
little over four years uh resistance
training experience so these were
experienced subjects now what did uh you
put one through more of a bodybuilding
type oriented program and one through
more of a powerlifting what uh were the
parameters with the bodybuilding versus
powerlifting yeah so what we were trying
to do the the essence of this and this
actually was my dissertation uh study we
were trying to look at uh a group that's
doing training primarily through
mechanical tension to maximize
mechanical tension which would be
powerlifting type routine versus a group
that's looking to maximize metabolic
stress and and still have some obviously
keeping uh mechanical tension high but
not not as high as you would in a
powerlifting but also have significantly
more metabolic stress which is very
similar what bodybuilders do so the
powerlifting group did uh seven sets of
three reps with three minutes rest and
they used a total body routine so in
that way you minimize metabolic stress
uh and maximize mechanical tension and
the bodybuilding group did as most
bodybuilding uh programs do did a split
routine where they train multiple uh
exercises and the same workout for a
given muscle group and they did uh three
sets of 10 uh with 90 seconds rest so
shorter rest intervals uh more
repetitions fewer sets we equated the
volume now why why equate volume Brad
like you know bodybuilders and
powerlifters train differently if you
really want to know what's best why
would you equate
volume well again when you're doing
research studies you want to look at
different parameters so what I wanted to
do here was to make sure that the Vol we
know that volume there is a an effect of
volume on hyper that volume is highly
correlated at least up to a given
threshold with hypertrophy more volume
equals more hypertrophy I wanted to rule
that out so if you're looking at
metabolic stress versus high metabolic
stress versus high mechanical tension I
didn't want to be a someone to say well
they did more volume so really that's
blown out of the water in future studies
I will look at doing a nonv volume
equated let's say three sets of three
versus three sets of 10 that's something
you can do in the future so you want
control the volume this way you can just
look hey the volume was the same it was
just that uh load was higher and load
and rest was higher in the run one group
and then uh shorter in in the other
group correct and what did you find well
first of all what did you use to measure
hypertrophy hyy was done through a
ultrasound diagnostic ultrasound and um
we did strength measures as well we did
one RM squat one RM bench press I I did
um the ultrasound we did bicep I also
did quads unfortunately we were not able
to get enough reliability in the
quadricep measurements uh so we only
were able to report the biceps I will
say that the uh so the biceps so the
findings were that hypertrophy was
really very similar if not almost
identical between the two groups and the
biceps uh like I said I did not report
the quadriceps but from the the subjects
that I was able to get good enough scans
there was not not significant
differences which just wasn't
statistically viable to report that
because of the non-reliable nature so
basically the you got similar
hypertrophic adaptations between a
bodybuilding and a powerlifting routine
corre now here's something interesting
that you uh talked about in the
discussion section the time
commitment y so talk about that yeah
well first of all and there was um
significantly greater streng gains uh in
the in in the squat and there was a
trend for it in the bench press as well
um for the powerlifting group for the
powerlifting group correct so if you
want to be stronger train for
powerlifting if you want to be bigger
what would you say the edge goes to yeah
well so here's the thing and this is why
you have to take certain things with a
grain of salt uh so we showed
mechanistically that the metabolic
stress or at least this is what I infer
from it that uh metabolic stress uh
versus mechanical tension that really
they kind of cancel each other out that
uh instead of being um synergistic and
additive where my theory originally was
that hey if you keep mechanical tension
high and then you increase metabolic
stress it'll have an additive effect at
least seems from this study that is not
the case that if volume is equated that
the they kind of cancel each other out
that if you have lower mechanical
tension uh with greater metabolic stress
it'll come up to the level of the
metabolic stress of the mechanical
tension however as you just mentioned
there are some caveats number one the uh
the commitment in time took 70 minutes
for the uh powerlifting group it was 17
minutes for the bodybuilding group so
ultimately as I mentioned before that
increasing volume is extremely important
uh at least up to a certain point in I
pery you just wouldn't have been able to
do enough volume add on enough exercises
for a total body routine we were only
able to do G back and and quads and and
glutes basically so we're very limited
in the number of exercises that can be
included because of the constraints put
on for a true hypertrophy routine it
would take three hours to go through
that in a powerlifting type fashion uh
just you couldn't you couldn't add
enough volume in to equate that so so
what's nice is that 70 minutes of
powerlifting versus 17 minutes of
bodybuilding routine gets similar levels
of hypertrophy so people who are in a
time crunch they can do higher reps slow
rest periods and get similar levels of
hyper hypertrophic gains that's to me
that's important to know but if you're
going you have the ability so here's the
other caveat though is that three three
of the subjects uh that got injured were
um I'm sorry the two of the subject the
two subjects that got injured were in
the powerlifting group and every one of
the powerlifting subjects on exit
interviews said they were toast that
basically they were they needed a Deo
and they just were ready for for a
different type of routine they were
really at their end and the bodybuilding
group all to a man said I could they
were ready to train with more volume
which is interesting because in the ne
in a upcoming study that we'll talk
about the 30
rep wasn't the the opposite was the case
the high rep yeah that's a story for a
different day but just sticking with
this one so the bottom line here is that
really the hyper if your goal is pure
hypertrophy um the the hypertrophy range
really is a valid range mostly because
it's just an efficient strategy to
achieve hypertrophy within a given uh
time frame and and within the
constraints of volume if you've got 20
minutes to train the most effective way
is
through you know typical bodybuilding
parameters High Reps higher reps low
rest periods yeah if if you have that or
I mean if you have an hour to train as
well because you can keep it I could
have done three times the volume in the
and and gotten better high purchas if
you equated time if you equated time and
not volume that's the bodybuilding group
would have seen better results that's
correct and and the on the other side if
your goal is pure strength combination
then the powerlifting did see better
strength Gaines I will say that the if
you look at the numbers while it was
statistically greater and if your goal
is just to maximize strength yes the
powerlifting group did see better gains
but the bodybuilding style group did see
very good gains as well it wasn't like
they were they they had poor strength
gains so well statistically significant
means that it just doesn't occur by
chance that's important to know the
absolute values were not hugely in favor
it was a it was a fairly decent amount
3% or so greater but certainly nothing
that would say wow you're going to be
weak if you're training in in 10 reps
okay we're 10 minutes in and we've only
talked about one study because you've
been blabbering way too
much next dudy what's the title Brad
yeah the next one is regional
differences in muscle activation during
hamstrings exercise and this was just
published a couple weeks ago again
Journal strength and conditioning
research so this study uh we wanted to
we Brad and I were uh we we've talked
about this a lot over the years there
was a study that I actually was listed
on this paper my friend Jordan mut
menucha from Spain we used functional
MRI to uh examine um muscle damage uh
two days following a a hamstring workout
and we used the lunge versus the um
Ecentric lying leg curl and it showed
that the upper hamstrings were more
damaged in a lunge and the lower
hamstrings were more damaged in a leg
curl but no study had ever looked at
just simple EMG Activation so um we
wanted to look at a kind of like a pure
hip flexion extension exercise and then
a pure knee flexion extension exercise
and uh so we picked the this the
straight Leed deadlift versus the lying
leg
curl uh electrodes placed on the upper
and lower uh biceps Fus long head and
then uh semi enosis right Brad yeah
correct so we did the basically you'd
look at the lateral hamstrings which
would be the biceps uh biceps for morus
and the uh medial hamstrings which be
semit tendonosis semiosis would
certainly have some effect there as well
and our hypothesis Brad explain what our
hypothesis was yeah the hypothesis was
that um so first of all it should be
noted that the hamstrings is a partition
muscle
uh certainly the semitendinosis semiosis
have been shown to be compartmentalized
where they're inovated by different
nerves and they terminate the uh fibers
terminate intrafascicular
uh whereas the the biceps florus the
long head uh crosses the hip joint
whereas the short head does not so there
was certainly reason to feel that the
leg curl in you've also you've got
different length changes taking place
with the proximal fibers uh the fases
are longer and they shorten more than
the distal fibers so it would make it
would it wouldn't so our hypothesis was
go ahead well that the the uh stiffle
deadlift would recruit more in the upper
uh portion of the hamstring and that the
lead curl would have greater recruitment
in the lower portion of the hamstrings
and was our hypoth this is confirmed uh
in part it was so the lead curl showed
greater activity
substantially markedly and significantly
greater activity in the lower aspects of
both lateral and medial hamstrings uh
whereas the stiff-legged deadlift and
the leg curl had approximately equal
activity in the upper portion of the
HRS so that surprised me Brad I I would
have I thought that the uh upper
hamstrings would get worked more in the
straight-legged deadlift but the goes to
show you the leg curl is a good
hamstring exercise and um it would imply
that uh like if people say just deadlift
for hamstrings that they're they'd be if
you did a long long-term training study
a longitudinal study would you predict
Brad that a group that did just just
like volume equated deadlift versus
deadlift plus light curls would you
predict greater hamstring hypertrophy
with the com combined group you're
talking about dead lips or stiff deads
well the I think one study showed
activation between deadlifts and
straight leg deadlifts is similar for
hamstrings but uh I mean I mean because
in a in a regular deadlift you're
bending at both the knees and basic
paper I have the paper it was it shows
similar
activation anyway it doesn't really
matter if it was R I certainly say yeah
look one thing that I CLE clearly has
been shown is that the squad and the leg
press uh do not engage the hamstrings
anywhere near to the extent that an
isolated move does like a lead curl or
stiff like a deadli so certainly they
it's extremely important if you want
well-developed hamstrings to have a uh
complimentary I don't like to use
isolated but a uh single joint move
where you're keeping the joint fixed at
one end while training it at the other
and yes I would say that you will see
greater development now one thing that's
important real quick this study
indicates two single joint moves would
be needed well at least a knee flexion a
knee flexion would be needed if you
wanted to maximize lower hamstring
hypertrophy but but bear in mind this
isn't a hypertrophy study this is an EMG
study youd need a follow-up study to
look at hypertrophy and that's the point
that I wanted to make is that what we
don't know so certainly we're seeing
greater activation whether that greater
activation does translated into greater
hypertrophy has not been well
established there is some research that
we actually touched on this in one of
our previous episodes so there is some
research that where the activation is
occurring uh does correlate with greater
hypertrophy but uh in my view that is
that still needs to be developed more
was that research with EMG or was it
with MRI was with MRIs I remember that
is correct wakahara did both studies
right that's correct uh but the uh MRI
has been shown to correlate to EMG y i I
agree okay we got role next
study and next is uh one that I did with
um my good friend and colleague man
henselman which is the effect of interet
rest intervals on Resistance exercise
induced muscle hypertrophy just pubbed
ahead of print in the Journal sports
medicine and this was a review paper
just published had a print two days ago
right a couple days ago yeah and this
was a review paper where we at we looked
at the effect of rest intervals and
whether it C correlates to where the
shorter rest intervals as usually is
discussed correlates to Greater
hypertrophy and what did you
find that that really is not the case
that certainly there is a logical basis
a theoretical basis where uh shorter
rest intervals might contribute to
Greater hypertrophy and that's basically
because there's greater metabolic stress
there also greater
hypoxia greater at least acute cell
swelling whether but it doesn't seem at
least in The Limited number of studies
that is not actually panned out in
practice so what I will say is that the
the literature is very uh Limited in
terms of what uh the studies the
controlled studies You' think that this
is something that's been well
established really is only two studies
that have directly looked at it and
there's some severe limitations within
those studies I just did a blog post on
this but that said based upon what we
can determine through the research uh it
would seem that
um my best
um I I would say from looking at the
research my best analysis would be that
if there is an effect it would be small
uh and and at least at this point it
doesn't seem that there is an effect so
from from what we
have I'll tell you um one kind of thing
that I take home is that um so like with
your classic hypertrophy paper about the
three mechanisms I think that it's wise
to to kind of combine both strategies so
you know have an exercise where you do
rest a little bit longer and really go
for maximiz ma maximizing tension and
then have uh an exercise where you rest
less and maybe do higher reps and really
aim for maximizing metabolic stress and
trying to get the pump and and some cell
swelling and um you know to me that
makes good sense but that that has not
been shown either in the research
correct that's never been looked at the
com so these are things again these are
some limitations of research so the like
I said so one one study there's been two
real studies that have been done that
have done it in a controlled fashion one
looked at two minutes rest versus five
minutes rest now two minutes you start
to dissipate lot of the metabog stress
starts to dissipate as far as the
buildup and certain with your sell
swelling hypoxia so is that a true
effect like the classic body building 60
to 90 seconds I'd say no it's I it was a
good study but there were limit a that
the other study they used a um they used
anthropometric measurements to look at
hypertrophy which is just a bad it's I
know they've said it was validated but
I've I've seen those types of uh of
instrument of
um analyses used and it really does not
equate very well it's highly subject can
be highly unreliable highly subject to
user error researcher error so I I'm not
confident in that what I would say is
that really we need a lot more studies
and until then I think like you said
it's good to to use different rests a
lot of it comes down to uh intuitiveness
I think if you're obviously if you're
going to really compromise your the
mechanical tension where you're just not
feeling it it's not going to work either
so it's a very uh very untapped area of
research that we will be looking at I
think good good lifters figure out a
good yeah I've got and it depends what
your goal is is if it's strength
obviously I have got powerlifting
friends they rest 10 minutes in between
sets you know well strength is a
different certainly agre but it that you
know these guys are pulling 700 lbs and
you know deadlifting 700 pounds it's you
know and and they've been lifting a lot
of years the beginner probably doesn't
need you know they're not as strong but
also probably depends on the exercise um
when you're doing a smaller Mass
exercise you're your cardiov vascular
system recovers quicker and probably if
you if you were to have decreases in
Central Drive or anything like that from
the the set before that's going to
recover a lot quicker so um again that's
what I like about using both strategies
but uh let's let's move along we're 21
minutes in uh yeah next is um an electro
electromyographic comparison of a
modified version of the plank with a
lone lever and posterior tilt versus the
traditional plank exercise and this uh
was just accepted in the uh Journal
sports biomechanics and should be
published within the next couple weeks
but there isn't a link to it right now
huh there's not no
y so this one uh Brad and I God we
started this a long time ago and uh this
has been a pain in the ass to get
published and I don't know why it's a
really good paper it's just funny the
the the publishing world is very
unpredictable sometimes you can have a
paper that you think is a
no-brainer uh you know get rejected or
take time to you know and then you can
have one that you're worried about that
flies right through but uh what is
Kramer's uh William Kramer's philosophy
uh every paper will have a have the
right home if you look for it something
to that effect so you need to you know
submit to different journals and keep
cranking away and we got this published
so one of the journals that we submitted
to said that it's not not relevant and
I'm going this is very relevant this is
this is going to be a very popular
article but you know what sometimes the
people in the journal have their own
interests and it might not interest them
so anyway describe the paper Brad yeah
so what we did was we looked at a plank
with a l lever and posterior tilt so
this was a modified version of the
traditional Plank and I I will say that
uh my good buddy uh what's his name uh
the glute guy contras turned me on to
this and got me interested in in
actually carrying out a controlled study
and what we did was we looked at four
variations of the planks we looked at a
traditional Plank and the lone lever
posterior tilt means the lone lever is
where you bring your elbows way up high
towards your eyes and the posterior tilt
is basically where you squeeze your
glutes uh so we looked at the
traditional plank which is just the
regular girl old fashioned plank then we
looked at a plank that just had a
posterior tilt just the plank that had
the lung lever and then the plank the
lung lever posterior tilt so we looked
at four versions we gave them rest in
between we
counterbalanced uh the study so that the
versions were carried out at different
times so fatigue wouldn't enter in and
what we found so it was interesting we
we start real quick what was
our did we list this in the paper our
hypothesis I don't remember whether we
listed it in the paper but certainly our
hypothesis the central hypothesis was
well proved well we knew that we knew
from previous studies that the plank
does not activate the core musculature
very well let
um so we knew that these all the the
three non-traditional variations would
exceed but and we knew that obviously
the hardest would be the uh combining
the two the long lever with the
posterior pelvic tilt but I had a
feeling that the posterior pelvic tilt
would have more of an effect on the
abdominal musculature than the long
lever did you think that too Brad um I
was inclined to think that way as well
uh and that actually was disproved that
the long lever they both they were
synergistic so adding both of them
together had a greater effect than
either alone but the lung lever
contributed a greater amount to the
effects and we looked at all the so we
looked at the major core muscles The
Superficial muscles the rectus abdominis
the
obliques um the so we looked at upper
rectus lower rectus obliques and the um
erector SP the erector spine a none of
them got more than like 8% of MVC the
the plank is not a good erector exercise
it's a you know anterior core exercise
but uh I can't remember the levels of
activation Brad but the long lever
posterior pelvic tilt is through the
roof off the charts I mean it's a very
challenging so if you training people
and you don't have equipment you can
give them this plank version and have a
very effective core stability exercise
um one thing that was interesting Brad
is the inter
uh individual variation between
different people and it just goes to
show you how different some people are
and this goes for every exercise and
that's why it's important to have an
ample um ample sample size because we
have some people that uh just the simple
plank worked the hell out of their core
and other people who barely worked them
it's just very you know very the V the
variation is pretty high yeah when
you've done as many EMG studies as we
have one of the things you realize is
how different people are in terms of the
way they activate muscles and uh now a
good body this is why like a bodybuilder
can decide which muscles they want to
recruit and by having a mind to muscle
connection uh engage that muscle to a
much greater degree but the average
person they're going to they're going to
get the best uh activation patterns that
their body wants to uh just without
thinking about it so their body will
naturally if you will try to get greater
activation through certain mus muscles
based upon their body habitat and other
factors awesome okay we're 26 s minutes
in 3 minutes we got one more study to
discuss yeah and this one is currently
in review right now so uh we can talk a
little about it but it's muscle
activation during low versus high load
resistance training and well-trained Men
let's not tell where it's in review at
at this point but it's at a major
journal uh and it's uh hopefully in the
last we've gotten comments back from the
reviewer which we've answered and
hopefully those will it will be
satisfactory but you want to give a
little insight into
this
um this was the uh the leg press versus
uh the 30 reps uh sorry uh 75% versus
30% loads we looked at uh vases what was
it vasus lateralis rectus femoris vasus
medialis and then also biceps femoris so
we looked at three quad muscles and then
one hamstring
muscle well and basically we did the leg
press exercise and we had uh one group
do you know uh as many reps as they
could with um actually we we the the we
didn't split them into two groups they
did both right yeah this was a within
subject design so we it was a two-day
protocol the first day first testing day
they did a 1 RM on the leg press and
then we brought them back within 72
hours hours or so after they did the 1rm
and we then tested them at 75% of the
1rm and 30% we counterbalanced it so
that one the first subject would be 75%
one RM first and then 30% and the other
one would be 30% first then 75 and that
way again you make sure there's no uh
issues with fatigue entering into this
and um what we found was clearly the 75%
had greater activation in all the muscle
studed real quick Brad lay lay the
foundation here what's the the theory
here is
that the size principle discussed the
size principle yeah the theory is is
that if you train to muscle fatigue and
all these sets were carried out to True
muscle failure that if you train to
muscle failure that you will get equal
activation uh basically that the failure
will make the muscles uh recruit all the
available fibers at Beyond a certain
point and what we found is that is not
the case at least at the level study so
75 versus 30 the 30% did not ultimately
achieve uh the same activation wasn't
anywhere even close so the it was really
a a wash out here now this is something
that's debated in the literature
carpanelli really was the first guy to
really start pushing the size principle
thing and basically saying the load
doesn't matter if you go to you know
momentary muscular failure you're going
to active
all the available type one and type two
motor units and
um we Brad and I
um over the years we've become big fans
of lighter weight for High Reps for
hypertrophy but for maximizing
activation we don't think we think
there's a a
range but it's probably higher than 30
you got to go higher than 30% one R Max
so this doesn't mean that the size
principle
isn't valid it just means there's
probably a certain threshold that you
have to get over and it might depend on
the exercise and the muscle groups that
are tested but surely with leg press and
Brad how many reps did uh the the you
got um the average number of reps with
the 30% load was like
50 I think it was 44 if I remember with
30% and I think it was like 14 with the
uh with the 7 25% yeah so but here's
what I would say Brett um at least
theoretically I would uh I would guess
that the issue here is that you're
getting a buildup of inorganic phosphate
uh and the acid base uh from the
disassociation of hydrogen ions
ultimately ends up interfering with the
contraction before the highest threshold
motor units can come into play that
would be my theory here is that just the
acidbase build up as well as the
inorganic phosphate could it also be
aerobic slightly what's that could you
also be like slightly aerobic and you're
getting
recovery I don't know what you mean
slightly a but but here's the other
thing and this is you because I've done
a lot of my own research on this with
like certain GL on the glutes when they
do body weight squats you won't see
glute activation keep going up but if
you do band hip thrust they do it needs
to have constant tension and with the
leg press you might
you blood might you
know you need EXT we did see no but we
did see there was increased recruitment
so it wasn't it didn't stay flat oh yeah
yeah right right right recruitment but
it just didn't rise to anywhere near the
level but and real quick did we look at
the last 10 reps of the set for the yep
yeah yes we looked through all different
permutations so we would just uh first
of all we looked at mean which is the
average of all the Reps and we looked at
Peak and they were it was like 25%
greater Peak activation and 35% greater
mean activation then we looked at just
the last uh a given number of reps last
eight reps last 10 reps none of it
changed it was all just highly in favor
of the higher of the higher weight but
here's the other thing that's a very
important Point too so we are
investigating higher loads now to try to
look at where is this threshold so I
have a study we have a study going on
now that's looking at higher uh rates of
percentage 1 RM but it's not just the
recruitment it's also how long the
muscles are stimulated with the I'm
sorry the fibers muscle fibers are
stimulated so you can recruit it but if
it's just a twitch so let's say you
recruited it for for that half an
instant is that going to maximally
stimulated from a hypertrophic
standpoint well the the evidence would
suggest not that you need to keep it
stimulated for a given period of time so
just because you might get a peak let's
say the peak is even you also have to
look at the mean activation over a given
period and the these are things again
that it's just not very well delineated
in the research and hopefully we will
help to flesh this out over the coming
months and years and another interesting
thing to look at would be if you combine
the loads because maybe the lighter
light weight is better at uh growing the
type one fibers and the heavier weight
is better at growing the type two fibers
and if you did combine you might see
Superior results and I think there's a
study that's view right now that
actually uh has a theory about that but
we'll we'll save that for another
podcast okay anything to add Bradley no
that's it 34 minutes we did good cool
okay um check the blog I will have the
Links at least to three of them and I
hope you enjoyed episode number nine all
right